A Guide to the Isidor Steve Brody Papers, 1889-1978
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
Isidor Steve Brody Papers 1889-1978
Roanoke Public Libraries
1983.1.1
1 record storage box, 1 suitcase
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donor information unavailable.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born March 12, 1889 in Kiev Russia, Isidor Steve Brody came to the United States in 1906 at the age of 17. He became a U.S. citizen in 1912. In 1916, Brody enlisted in the army as a medic and fought with the American Expeditionary Force in France. He came to Roanoke in 1935, serving first at the Veterans Affairs Hospital in Salem, VA, then at the Veterans Affairs Regional office from 1946 until his retirement in December 1958. An active member of the community, Brody helped establish a unit of the United Service Organization and the first War Mothers Chapter in the Roanoke Valley. He was an active member in the American Legion, Veterans of Foreign Wars, and Disabled American Veterans ad received numerous awards and honors for his patriotism.
Roanoke World-News editor M. Carl Andrews said of Brody, "It requires a person born in a country without basic human rights to fully understand and demonstrate his love for our America...[n]o other person in Roanoke ever did so much to honor that [American] flag in his lifetime." He unselfishly made financial contributions to many civic organizations, most notably the Boy Scouts of America. Brody is best known for donating and placing a United States flag in almost every building in the City of Roanoke. (The last flag that he donated was at the dedication of the Roanoke Civic Center in 1971. The Steve Brody Room in the Main Library of the Roanoke Public Libraries was named in his honor in 1983. Remembered as Roanoke's Russian-born patriot, Brody died on November 20, 1978.
Scope and Content
The Isidor Steve Brody Papers are comprised of documents, photographs, and artifacts that relate to community work done by Brody in Roanoke from 1953-1978. Documents include a biographical timeline of military service, news clippings, awards, stars of David, war enlistment cards, Christmas cards (including images of local families) and correspondence (1951-1977). Photographs and negatives include portraits of Brody from WW I - 1978, public events (flag dedication ceremonies, picketing during Vietnam, festivals in Elmwood Park and Victory Stadium); streetscapes and local buildings; small group photos (award ceremonies, WDBJ 7 TV man of the week award ceremony); and collages of awards, news clippings, and photographs of Brody. Artifacts include war registration cards, wallets with all personal contents, a scrapbook, yamikas, suitcase, flag and various awards and trophies.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged by document format and chronilogically there under. Photographs and negatives were seperated and organized by subject. Artifacts are arranged according to type and size. The Isidor Steve Brody Papers had no original order at the time of donation.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Index Terms
Isidor Steve Brody; Brody; Roanoke Virginia
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1951-1977
  - Correspondence, 1951-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes pictures of local Roanoke families.
  - Correspondence re: Security National Bank (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Framed Letter, March 10, 1975 (Other Suitcase, Item 9)
    'In the Council of the City of Roanoke, Virginia, the 10th day of March, 1975.' Attached on letter is gold seal with purple ribbon.
- Artifacts
  - Star of David (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ID Bracelet, cuff links, ivory pocket knife), Items placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 20)
  - Beaver Badge, Item placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 22)
  - Tweezers, key holder, scissors, Items placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 23)
  - Contents of wallet, Items placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 24)
  - Key pouch., Item placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 25)
  - Trophy (cup on wood stand) 1972 (Othertype Suitcase, Item 1)
    Trophy reads 'To my good Samaritan friend Steve Brodie from Saunders Guerrant 1972
  - United States Flag (Othertype Suitcase, Item 3)
  - Yamika (black) (Othertype Suitcase, Item 11)
  - Wallet (empty) (Othertype Suitcase, Item 12)
  - Bill holder (plastic) (Othertype Suitcase, Item 13)
  - Wallet (with contents) (Othertype Suitcase, Item 14)
- Photographs & Negatives
  - Collages and Signs (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portraits of Steve Brody (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Public Events Photographs (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Streetscapes & Buildings (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Small groups (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Negatives (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Framed portraits of Steve Brody (2) (Box 1, Item 19)
  - Framed Photo collage of Steve Brody (black & white) 1916-1918, 1955, 1956 (Othertype Suitcase, Item 2)
  - Scrapbook (Othertype Suitcase, Item 5)
    Entitled "Photographs" in dark red lettering. Contains newspaper articles, pictures and magazine clippings containing information about Steve Brody.
  - Baby lying on its back (black & white image) (Othertype Suitcase, Item 6)
  - Five color circle portraits of a woman, a young girl and three young boys. (Othertype Suitcase, Item 7)
- Biographical Information
  - News clippings re: Steve Brody (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Timeline (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Documents re: Civil Service Commission (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Certificates & Awards
  - Awards (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Raleigh Court Library Dedication (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Collage of certificates, letters and photographs, Framed. (Box 1, Item 16)
  - Collage of certificates, photographs, and news articles, Two framed images nailed together. (Box 1, Item 17)
  - Roanoke Valley Chamber of Commerce resolution re: Roanoke Citizen of Honor, Steve Brody., Framed. (Box 1, Item 18)
  - Award lapel pins, Items placed in an artifact box. (Box 1, Item 21)
  - Certificate, 'Boy Scouts of America the Silver Beaver Award for Distinguished Service to Boyhood' and article 'Civitans Select Good Samaritan', Two items framed together. (Othertype Suitcase, Item 8)
  - Award, 'National Conference of Christians and Jews presents its brotherhood citation to Steve Brody' (Othertype Suitcase, Item 10)
  - Silver Beaver Award Box (Othertype Suitcase, Item 15)